okay so about seven years ago I started
a text to teach a text to the local
students in Arizona and then I got very
busy the last few years and I didn't
teach it for a while and I started again
in Sedona because we had two extra days
and it was so much fun and it's related
to the lions dance that I thought I get
to have two classes during the lamb room
when I'm supposed to do something more
fun and something special so I decided
to do this book with you guys okay so
we'll do it tonight and we'll do it next
week sometime this is called dungeon
Shang Shang Depp's a dungeon Shang de
Duncan shunda means debate a fight
between an angel and a devil okay in one
person's mind inside of one person's
mind and it's a poem and it's very long
in seven years I finished 11% so I will
be 125 when we finished so and this
written by the first punch in number
okay
so he was very very unusual llama a very
very great poet
and a very very great philosopher and a
great man I'd like to tell the story he
did a lot of long retreat you know cape
and one day there was two armies are
going to attack each other outside of
his cave in the valley like over here or
something and he was meditating and his
he also has a venerable Jigme his
venerable jing-mei
knock on the door that came you know and
he said I told you I'm doing between and
his venerable jing-mei said excuse me
but there's going to be a war here this
afternoon maybe we want to leave you
know then he said war who's fighting he
said two big armies are coming together
to Tibetan armies are fighting each
other he said they're gonna upset my
retreat then he said don't worry I'll
take care of it so he went down he broke
his retreat he went down in the valley
one Army's coming this way one Army's
coming this way then he stood between
them he said you guys want to fight you
have to kill me first and he's very very
famous Lama at that time he said you
have to kill me first you know you can
kill me first
who's going to kill who's going to shoot
the first arrow you know I will stand
here you know then everyone's afraid to
shoot you know then he said let the two
generals come to talk to me privately
then the two armies are waiting and the
two generals this would make a good
movie I think two generals come he said
look you guys fight today one of you is
going to lose and many people will die
and I have suggestion then they said
what he said I'm a big Lama I'm very
rich I have a lot of gold I will give
half to
general and you go home don't fight
they're like good idea so he gave his
general goal and they canceled the war
and people asked me should Buddhist
people be involved in politics or you
know if if you involve like that I think
it's good you know so he he doesn't want
them to kill each other and he stopped
them okay so he wrote this poem a very
famous poem and my teacher taught us
about half of it and then he couldn't
finish and so I'm gonna start at a
special place I'm gonna the the English
will be here okay I translated the first
half or something and in this part
inside one man's mind there's a devil
talking and angel talking okay the angel
is wisdom okay angel is understanding
emptiness okay
and the devil thinks that the husband
who yell at you come from him
not from you okay the devil supports a
wrong idea
pen comes from pen not from me okay not
from my sneeze okay like that so they
are fighting there's a war inside of one
person's mind okay there's a famous
Christian book by CS Lewis who wrote
Narnia tales it's called Screwtape
Letters and it's very beautiful if you
have time to read it it's very short
very famous English book in that one
young man started to get interested in
spiritual life then the devil want to
change his mind
so the devil sent his nephew to the
earth to try to change this young man's
mind and so the letter the whole book is
letters written by the devil to his
nephew about how to ruin a young man's
life you know how to make the young men
unhappy and it's a beautiful beautiful
book you know and I heard an interview
with the author and he said it was very
difficult to write this book because I
have to think like a devil you know
whole book I have to think what will the
devil say you know and this is the same
this poem is very similar okay so
because we are talking about lions dance
and because the lion stance has nine
parts which you learn so far if you're
good I will teach you some more okay I
will check after retreat there's five
parts to that lions dance taught by
Buddha in the shot Sahasra progeny
paramita borobudur Amida Sutra jinn he
taught this lion stance nine part
meditation first eight parts of the
meditation are wrong meditations they
are only they are like breathing
meditation just to exercise your mind
make your mind strong but there's no
content which will help you it's just
interesting it's deep it's feels good
it's exciting and you're not supposed to
stop you're supposed to use them to go
to the meditation number nine okay now
the first panchen lamas book is very
interesting because in this first
quarter of the book
the devil starts to make a list of
meditations he likes he likes them he
says I like it when people use these
meditations why I feel very comfortable
in their mind okay it means they are
like for example first one is trying to
think about nothing okay now there's a
principle of this book that you have to
understand okay there's a principle like
if you come home and your husband says
something hard to you some sales bad
word to you okay if you come home you're
tired you want a hug and instead the
husband say something bad to you like
you're stupid okay there's two ways you
can look at that husband okay
number one the normal way you know he
had a bad day he's unhappy
you know he's hungry I didn't fix dinner
yet you know he's he's feeling bad today
and he called me bad word okay
then that state of mind thinks husband
comes from the husband and that state of
mind thinks the husband decided to call
me stupid okay then that's one state of
mind okay then there's another state of
mind okay
when the husband says you are stupid
then this is an educated Buddhist state
of mind educated Buddhist correct
educated Buddhist then they look at the
silver eggs and their mind and they say
oh I remember last week I called my kids
stupid okay I remember I did that and I
heard myself call my kids stupid and
that
sound made an impression on my mind and
that impression became a sanskara
in sanskrit fresh seed and then that
became a vasana which means ripe scene
and then it and then when i came home
this evening it it opened and husband
picture came from here and the husband
is yelling at me you're stupid ok so I
always like to ask people how can you
prove that your husband is correct yeah
you call him stupid but ok then your
husband was correct ok if you want to
prove you're stupid then call him stupid
I'm not stupid you're stupid ok then you
make a new seat next week the kids are
bad coming from you you get angry at
them you call them stupid you plant
another seed you come home after five
days husband call you stupid
you call husband stupid that's called
what in Sanskrit samsara samsara circle
circle you're stupid no you're stupid no
you're stupid no you're stupid no you're
stupid how many lifetimes do you have to
do that before you stop before you
figure it out ok what's the correct
thing to do husband says you're stupid
you just say yes
okay I'm still okay now the state of
mind which thinks the husband decided to
call it stupid and the state of mind
that understands the husband is coming
from your seeds they are completely
incompatible in one mind they cannot
stay in one mind at the same time okay
they're like in the cowboy there's a
cook the cowboy say there is no room in
this town for both of us you have to
leave or I will kill you
then I know what to know you have to
leave or I will kill you then it means
that inside this place here those two
ideas cannot stay someone has to go
someone has to go so this is a very
funny book the first pension mama calls
this your apartment this is your
apartment and only one person can stay
in the apartment devil or angel okay
why angel understand the husband comes
from their own see the devil thinks the
opposite they cannot control the mind at
the same time one of them has to go okay
understand impossible to have both in
the same mind at the same time okay can
they go like this
yeah husband call you stupid one time
you're like oh wait that's a geshe
michael talk about ok then they say you
already stupid then you're like I heard
a big Lama he talk like this you know he
said first time someone call you stupid
you should smile ok second time they
call you stupid you should be like yeah
alright ok third time they call you
stupid you can say kappa soul
okay then there are 5000 people
listening there American people
listening to this llama I start laughing
only one one person in five thousand
haha my friend say why are you laughing
I said you know what he just said one
kappa some is eat don't learn the
word okay then that translator was like
this you should tell them you don't like
it then I'm like okay so anyway it's
possible these twos it's possible the
angel stays for the first time the angel
stays the second time then finally the
angel get tired and the devil come and
say no kept us all okay all right so but
they cannot stay in the same mind at the
same time now the whole idea of his book
the whole idea and you have to
understand is if you meditate if you
meditate the goal the only goal of
meditation is to create some situation
where the devil has to live hastily no
choice okay
some kind of understanding has to be you
know level 9 in the lions dance
meditation okay I asked you first
eight levels of the lion stance
meditation can the devil stay in the
apartment or not yeah why oh look at
your breath Devils like hey you can look
at your breath your whole life you just
stay here come on let's do this
meditation there's a good meditation
yeah okay no problem you know oh you
want to listen to the
air conditioner yeah you're my friend
you can stay in my apartment you know
you can stay in this apartment oh you
want to pretend there's no thought in
your mind everything turn off your mind
oh that's comfortable for me you could
do that meditation for 10 years you can
sit with me don't think about anything
we are friends you can live with me no
problem okay but if you reach number 9
meditation right if you start meditating
that your husband come from you and
there's no husband who didn't come from
you which is called what function okay
now that one the devil starts to get
uncomfortable you know no don't do that
tormenting on it why then I will have to
leave you know I cannot stay here okay
that idea it I cannot live with that
idea in the same mind don't do that
it's like someone like a big fart or an
in a small room you know then you you
like or her to go understand okay so the
principle the principle of this book is
to study many kinds of meditation and
then decide one thing what's done will
the devil have to leave the mind if you
do this meditation that's all that's all
that's the goal of the whole book okay
he examines twenty five systems of
meditation he examines twenty five
systems of meditation one by one and
then he checks them he describes them
correctly and then he says do you think
the devil can stay in a person's mind
if they are doing this meditate
okay and then so 25 of them are wrong
one of them is correct okay why why are
the 25 wrong now you tell me why are
they not meditation because the devil
can stay in the mind if you do them it's
comfortable for him okay you watch your
breath for 10 years
Vipassana watch your breath the devil's
like very comfortable there that's no
problem
that's not threatening to the devil okay
got it got it so he's gonna describe
twenty five meditations that don't
bother the devil okay
then he's gonna describe one which does
bother the devil because then the devil
has to move out okay got it
as long as the devil is in your mind you
will be unhappy and you will suffer and
you will do bad things to people and you
will die quietly okay no hope for you
you can never become a boner okay as
long as it devil is there the it's
impossible to become Buddha you will
suffer for years and years okay so we
want to find a meditation which makes
the devil uncomfortable
okay got it that's the whole purpose of
this poem
okay so I did some of them already in
Sedona but I'm gonna do the first ten
quickly just so you know now remember
and it's there are 26 meditations here
one of them makes the devil leave the
apartment okay only one of them
it's it's the same as what we did today
meditation number nine okay now I'm
gonna describe the meditation I will
scroll through the
Tibetan and the English you can look at
I will send you the whole text if you're
interested okay you can have for free it
doesn't matter and I put the Tibetan you
can check it is geshe michael crazy I
always put the Tibetan everything I do I
put the Tibetan so you can check ok ok
so now here starts to 26 okay here
starts to 26 and the Devils talking yeah
I can do that mmm is that better he says
yeah some people they in there I'm a big
meditator I have a special meditation
and they say I'm gonna I'm gonna throw
you out of this vine okay people
threaten me who's me people threaten me
I'm gonna kick you out of my mind yeah
how are you gonna do that I have
meditation
I'm meditation master okay yep tell me
what's the meditation okay here's the
first one okay stay in the present
moment
stay in the present moment okay
we use it in DCI we use it in DCI it's
not a goal but we use it like the eight
non meditations okay so I'm not asking
you does it does it cause you later -
see emptiness I'm not saying that I'm
saying now does it cause you okay ready
those eight help you to see emptiness
but they are not meditation they are not
meditation drinking green drink also
helps you to see emptiness but it's not
meditation even going to a wreathes yoga
class can help you to see emptiness but
it's not meditation okay got it
so my question is not you know does it
sharpen your mind green drink also
sharpen your mind okay my question is if
you do this meditation does the devil
have to leave your mind is it
incompatible
with the devil okay and this one is
don't think about the past don't think
about the future don't worry about
what's gonna happen tomorrow don't worry
about what your ex-husband said to you
okay live in the moment
focus now does that meditation is it
incompatible with the devil to stay in
your mind no okay got it
you see why we're going now I'm gonna
ask you 25 more times
that's only the first one it's called
present moment meditation okay okay stay
in the present moment no hopes no
regrets don't worry what happened in
past don't make plans for tomorrow in in
English there's a famous book be here
now be here now but it doesn't hurt the
devil who creates all your suffering and
you're gonna die if you be here now you
will be here now be here now I'll be
here now I'll be here now but I'm not
kidding I'm not kidding okay it doesn't
hurt
some sorry it doesn't stop your
suffering okay
it doesn't stop your death okay that's
what we want okay we want to help the
whole world not to have this kind of
body okay just being in the present
moment it's it's it's a nice practice
it's useful for mental exercise but it's
not the Olympics okay there's no
Olympics in you guys okay there's no
Olympics in stretching okay
they don't have stretching Olympics
stretching is not the goal the run the
race is to go is it useful to be in the
present moment
you can focus you can do better business
you can pay attention to your kids more
carefully okay it's nice it's good it's
not gonna save your life
okay got it and we don't know how long
we have to live we don't have time to do
lower meditations we don't have time if
you guarantee me 50 years okay I'll do
one year of lower medicine okay
but if you say geshe-la might fall on a
stone tonight and die in his cottage and
tomorrow you have to go there and you
know it's possible right so we don't we
don't know when we're gonna die we don't
have time for lesser meditations okay we
don't have time we don't know how long
we have okay all right
if you know then okay first week you can
spend on this meditation okay next one
by the way in the end they not only
don't hurt the devil-dam meditating on
the devil why they are meditating on the
mind okay the minds not the devil the
mind holds the devil but the minds the
apartment come on what's the problem
with that every moment you spend in
meditation without challenging the devil
you are getting in the habit of not
challenging the devil okay it's
dangerous okay you are you're getting
used to living with the devil in your
mind okay and that's dangerous because
every karma is a habit we learned that
already okay all right next one the way
present moment meditators sees things
and the way I see things who's our devil
they're okay they can live together no
contradiction you can think about
present moment and be angry at your
husband okay no problem
I'm in the present moment I'm right here
now my husband called me stupid I call
him stupid I didn't think about
yesterday I didn't think about tomorrow
he's stupid right now okay it doesn't
hurt the devil okay how can they do any
damage to me in fact he says I don't
remember I ever met you in those
people's mind never ever once who's you
who's you the angel he says not only
this meditation doesn't hurt me I all
the people whose mind
I live in who are doing present-moment
meditation I never saw you there one
time you didn't even visit got it they
didn't think once about where did my
husband come from really you see they
just felt angry in the present moment
okay got it
you didn't even visit this apartment
okay got it Veronica told me don't say
just not wait wait until everyone
understands understand
okay angel came occasionally if you do
at least little bit correct meditation
what's correct mean is present moment
meditation in the DCI manual it is okay
is it correct it's not a meditation it's
not a meditation okay it's a focus in it
helps you focus your mind it's not a
meditation meditation should make the
devil uncomfortable okay we call it
meditation it's not real meditation okay
so when I say a meditation is wrong or
bad what I mean is what the word I like
to use is ineffective ineffective it
doesn't give you the result you need
okay I like to compare this meditation
and the other 24 to a company which
sells fire extinguishers to people that
they know don't work okay and that's
some kind of very what do you call it
cynical and cruel and greedy you know
there's a company in India I told this
story
I took a aspirin in India one time I got
very sick and I asked my Indian friend
you know I said I got very sick I took a
aspirin they said what kind of aspirin I
said you know like Rajesh aspirin they
say oh never take that aspirin I said
why I said they this company found out
rat poison is cheaper than aspirin and
they put rat poison in the aspirin
because it's cheaper okay you take it
cuz you're sick and then it kill you you
say I mean and and to be to be honest if
a meditation doesn't hurt the devil it's
like a fire extinguisher that doesn't
work and the company knows it
okay and and then you're gonna fire in
your kitchen and you pull it off the
wall and you push it in Boop nothing
happens
okay what's the fire your death okay
it's okay to do silly meditations when
you're young when you get older it
becomes more serious I don't have time
for silly meditations I I need something
that can put the fire out okay maybe I'm
gonna be a dog next life or I go to hell
I need a fire I need a real fire station
okay got it
okay all right here's number two in
effective meditation number two others
try to stop the mind from thinking about
anything their meditation is to be
careful not to think of anything at all
do you recognize this one which one
third formless realm meditation Chi Yong
man say to young me yeah think about
nothing remove all thoughts from your
mind
go into the void okay there's the
silence of an empty mind okay and does
it hurt the devil does it hurt the devil
no no effect on the devil okay you come
in the devil's apartment here devil's
been living here how long since forever
actually we're trying to evict him he
didn't pay rent
all that time okay millions of years he
didn't I read our job is to kick him out
you know it's time to leave you know
then if you think about nothing does it
threaten the devil no he doesn't care
he's like come on sit here next to me do
that meditation I love it
why because I will get stronger every
hour you spend in it I will get stronger
you
come sit next to me meditate about
nothing
empty your mind see the void you know
nothing okay got it
The Devil's very comfortable with that I
also can't remember that I ever saw you
in that person's mind ever who's you
angel what's the angel stand for wisdom
what's wisdom when your husband yells
are you he's coming from me that's all
he's coming from me okay if you really
understand emptiness it's impossible for
another human being to make you angry
cannot okay the more angry they get the
more you're like seeds see see see see
see see see my see my see oh ten of my
sins okay then can you blame yourself
it's my fault okay then no fight no
anger okay the devil has to move out
okay that's wisdom that's the angel okay
okay you're right this is not the angel
okay
here's number three ineffective
meditation number three this is a famous
mistaken meditation in ancient times
it's called shantung say Shenton and
this is a wrong idea about emptiness
okay
it's Geshe Michael dis flower I'm not
okay first of all I don't smell so good
okay so it's that flower part of me of
my body this body no it's over there
okay now this people who don't
understand penis they say look
cashy Michaels body is empty of the
flower it's true okay
the flower is not in my body you cut my
body open you won't find the flower okay
is it true Geshe Michaels body is empty
of that flower yes there's many kinds of
emptiness okay
will that help you the next time your
husband yells are you
he husband yell at you you are stupid
you say I'm not a flower it's true okay
it's true you are empty of flower but it
doesn't help you okay okay it doesn't
help son that's number three stupid as
an ineffective meditation okay
ineffective meditation
this is particular one is that the mind
is empty of being a physical thing that
flower is not geisha loss mind okay it's
my mind empty of that flower yeah that's
a physical my mind is mental
then it's not in my mind okay but that's
not the true nature of my mind now trick
question trick question
is it an emptiness of my mind the flower
it is my mind is empty a flower but it's
not real emptiness okay got it got it
my stomach's empty right now it's not
gonna take me to Nirvana
okay got it there's many empty right my
bank accounts empty it didn't take me to
Nirvana
not yet okay people who meditate on that
and by the way the school was called
John dogma the school was called John
number
it was about 600 years ago and it's gone
there's still a few people trying to do
it but it's it's a it's a bad idea it
just doesn't help anything okay then he
says those people were nowhere near you
who's you angel yeah okay got it
that one's easy okay here's another one
this is good to know these 25
meditations which are fire extinguishers
that don't work because you will hear
these in yoga studios in meditation
schools somewhere
almost every meditation you ever heard
in a yoga class is in these 25 so it's
good to get familiar with them because
your next yoga class there might be a
different one of the 25 okay then at
least you you know the principle okay
what makes a meditation ineffective not
useful what makes a meditation not
useful it doesn't hurt the devil okay
what's the devil wrong with you come on
telling your husband husband yeah the
husband is not my fault
you ready here's the ultimate expression
of ignorance ready take a deep breath I
didn't do anything he just yell at me I
can't open it all I didn't say anything
he's fiery me I didn't do anything okay
that's that's a devil talk perfect devil
time I didn't do anything he's not
yelling at me okay you always did
something there's no such thing as I
didn't do anything
okay got it
now this is called sim Jumba it's an old
bad idea it's called look at the naked
mind okay
focus on the naked mind okay
Buddhism says the mind has 52 or 51
mental functions attention memory
concentration wisdom ignorance there are
there are 51 52
some people say 46 different Buddhist
psychology system strip out all of those
takeaway memory take away intellect take
away jealousy take away wisdom what's
left is raw awareness okay in in Tibetan
it's called naked awareness gymba okay
so there's a kind of meditation where
you dig dig dig into the mind and you
take out it's like your brain surgeon
and you cut open the mind and you take
out memory take out attention
take out intellect take out and take out
compassion and what's left is the raw
mind knowing the the knower okay and
then some people think that's meditation
find the knower go down deep into the
mind to the center of the mind find the
one who knows the naked mind same
chamber and then this is meditation okay
will it hurt the devil not at all okay
that's our test of a meditation okay a
meditation should directly or indirectly
but rather directly hurt the demo okay
and this one doesn't
he's like you want to come sit in my
apartment and look at your naked mind
welcome come on okay you could sit here
your whole life waste your life on that
meditation and then I achieved my goal
which is your suffering okay got it
all right I never saw you in those
people's mind and it didn't hurt me at
all
okay who's talking the devil's talking
okay now this is called unstoppable mind
which is in Tibetan it's called the song
pal okay song tell and this is where you
let the mind okay what are we doing for
dinner what time we're gonna stop this
class kitchen Michael are we gonna have
a break do we get refreshments and you
just get out of the minds way okay let
the mind do his thing let him it's
almost like I'll kiss you but your
husband's there
okay Nick you can trust me yeah it's
it's almost like numbering okay I choose
to let the mind do whatever the mind
wants you know I will be passive I will
observe I will make no attempt to get
into the runaway a car called my mind I
won't get in the way of this vehicle
that has no driver okay I would just
stay out of the way and let the mind do
any crazy thing it wants okay
and they think this will bring greater
peace to the mind okay just stay out of
the way don't interfere your mind wants
to be jealous just step to the side let
the mind be jealous okay your mind is
worrying about stupid things just
because you're tired what's that thing
they taught us in NBC tired angry hungry
hungry and well it's the other one
hungry angry lonely tired and there's a
system of psychology that says don't
trust your mind under these four
situations when you are hungry and you
are angry when you're lonely when you're
tired don't trust about your mind is
saying okay and it's not a bad
instruction does it hurt that day long
maybe a little irritating okay okay all
right
and again I've never met you in those in
the minds of those people who say just
get out of the way let the mind do its
thing okay cause some tell right okay
next useless meditation trying to meet
the mind face to face with no training
okay no education so this is an idea
that you don't have to learn meditation
you just follow your natural instead
okay and you're just complicating things
if you go to as mama and you learn
meditation and you learn techniques of
meditation you're just making it too
complicated okay just relax you know be
here now you don't need to study
meditation method that's like studying
how to poopoo or something everybody
knows how to poopoo you know you don't
have to go to school and get it class
and how to poopoo okay really they think
that about meditation
you should let natural happen and you
don't need to learn meditation okay
every meditation is useful be nice don't
complain about other people's meditation
everything's good okay like that all
right you don't need to study okay next
one
now there was a school in Tibet that
said if you understand that
the devil is not there that's meditation
it's the devil in a human mind in
samsara of course they are yeah
but the Gardner said nothing exists and
nothing doesn't exist yeah
who said that I'll kiss you but you're a
nun okay but I'll hug you
yeah we have to say is it it does the
devil exist
yes can we say the devil is not there
yes in the same way that the second
husband is not there the husband who's
not coming from your seats was never in
him in your house never came to your
house the husband who's not coming from
your seats was never in your house okay
the devil seeing things wrong way that
didn't come from your sins was never in
the apartment here okay got it but it
doesn't mean that that was not there and
you don't have to do anything okay
that's a that's a mistake okay it's a
wrong understanding of what the Buddha
said nothing exists he means nothing
exists that doesn't come from your sins
okay so that that's obviously a hopeless
meditation I don't have to meditate to
fight the devil because the devil never
existed anyway because Buddha said that
it's a misunderstanding what Buddha
meant even even your wrong understanding
is coming from your seeds you planted it
okay
you planted it okay all right how many
we got bad meditation that was number
seven I don't know how many we're gonna
do
leftie
[Music]
this one is it's a long story but I'll
make it simple for you people who
discuss emptiness without using it at
home with their husband okay
people who dis in like universities okay
and they discuss the gardener and they
discuss chandrakirti in they discuss
middle-way and then they go home and
have a fight with their wife okay they
don't think they should use it okay so
it's called it's kind of like academic
discussions of emptiness that you don't
use with your family or you don't use
with your job you know
okay got it you you understand the
theory but you don't use it at home and
you don't use it in your business and
you don't use it with your health and
okay so that kind of meditation just
academic study about emptiness it's not
going to hurt the devil okay there are
many academic Buddhists who understand
the Sanskrit and the Tibetan and they're
very unhappy okay and they don't know
how to use it okay all right
then this is not a meditation but he
gives us he just gets a poetic sometimes
people are meditating on nothing more
than me sometimes they are meditating on
nothing more than nothing and sometimes
they are meditating I'm trying to think
of nothing okay now he mentions 26 but
he doesn't tell us what it is okay he
says a person who really meditates on
the seeds opening and creating the
things around them okay and the
emptiness of bubu lama those people that
contradicts how I look at things they
contradict me it's uncomfortable to be
with them and in fact when they enter
this apartment I have to leave okay but
there is common as a star which comes
out in the middle of the day
okay got it
except for this son all right then he he
he makes a little detour he says okay
until we come to a day when you can
change the situation don't talk to me
that you're gonna kick me out of the
mind who's talking Devils come on this
is the way it is I've been living here
forever you're new you that our body
went to die Mountain they studied for a
few hours they came home they want to
invite you into the mind but you just
knew I've been here forever okay so
don't talk about kicking me off
I'm the permanent resident of this
apartment you are Adam Barra
se-ah-dom Barra
it's a special flower in Buddhism it
opens every time a new Buddha comes to
this planet it opens once every thousand
years and once every ten thousand years
okay when that flower opens all the gods
get excited or Buddhist coming new next
Buddhist coming okay then devil call the
angel you are Odin brother you show up
every thousand years you know the person
go to Diamond mountain retreat they
learn for two weeks they come home they
meditate for a few days then you're here
for a little then you they get tired
they go back to their usual life come on
you are like this cobalt Lotus Blue
Lotus you think you're gonna kick me off
you you show up here once every thousand
years and you think you're gonna kick me
out get real okay to make you stay in
the mind this person that we are both
living in their head is gonna have to do
good karma all the time okay in fact the
only way you can make that much karma is
to have a llama and serve them who said
that
the dump yes I'm safe why you don't have
enough carbon it caused me trouble why
you didn't have a llama the only way to
make that much karma is to help someone
who's trying to help the whole world see
that's good karma be the DCI organizer
for Thailand you know a CI or a knife
you know then you make some serious
karma then maybe you can kick me out but
who doesn't who how many people do that
I'm safe man I'm saying you people who
serve the Dharma Michael Dunn present
you know running dining mountain maybe
he has enough seats to kick me out but
you other guys you don't even want to
watch to wash the dishes you know
I'm safe I'm okay in your mind got it
okay he what he means is that the Karma
to kick out the devil is heavy heavy
service of the Dermer heavy heavy
service like Jasmine go crazy for two
years to do Thailand the the morning
after Thailand retreat finish she look
relaxed then I say how about next year
did you say okay I'm the resonant Lord
but can we go straight we have another
40 minutes it's okay you don't need PP
okay if you have people you can donate
to Diamond Mountain okay you don't have
to just get up and go okay we are having
fun tonight this is the fun class this
is the easy class I live in this I am
the resident Lord I am the guy who rent
this apartment for a billion years
okay there's no other choice the only
way to get me out is to have the
opposite view of your husband it's
coming from me that there's no other
choice
yeah anyway everybody likes me and as
long as they like me they will never
have freedom okay next one okay here's
another meditation that people do decide
not to decide nothing is good nothing is
bad nothing is right nothing is wrong
okay like that don't make any decision
about anything okay just don't judge
people nothing's wrong somebody kills
somebody that's just something somebody
kissed somebody okay then don't decide
something's bad something's good okay
everything's the same everything is
empty right okay
this idea is so bad I can't stop
laughing when people talk about it who
said that
therefore he's like oh not no good no
bad
everything's illusion kill people kiss
people all the same that's great I love
them he's really we should make a play
out of this or something you know he's
like oh I love that one I really like
this one
so there's another one that in Buddhism
there's two realities right ultimate
reality and what's the opposite we call
deceptive reality okay why it's called
illusion why it fools you it tricks you
okay
it says I'm not coming from you I'm not
coming from you I'm not coming from you
okay that's called deceptive reality
everything except function everything
except emptiness in Buddhism we call
deceptive reality why it fools the mind
of anyone who's not a Buddha or an R
yeah okay it fools your mind
it says I'm coming I'm I'm not coming
from you I'm coming from my friend all
the pans talk to you like that all the
husband's talk to you like that okay I
don't coming from my side I'm not coming
from you okay got it
so actually the world is a lie it's an
illusion it's always lying to us okay
does it lie to a Buddha no okay
if a Buddha walks in the room is it
still deceptive reality we say yes
because the definition of deceptive
reality is that it falls a person who
doesn't understand emptiness okay that's
that's the definite it falls a energy
under an uneducated person okay don't
worry about it it's late so they think
that since the world is supposed to be
an illusion the mind must be an illusion
so I can meditate that my mind is an
illusion okay and that's a good
meditation if someone were to find
during their meditation that I was
something that didn't exist that would
damage me because I can't not
be here and be here too but until a
person reaches a meditation where they
see that I'm not what they thought I was
then the way we look at things is the
same no problem they can live in this
mind okay anyone who doesn't understand
that the devil is coming from seeds in
your mind that person they can meditate
all day it doesn't hurt me okay got it
I'll say it again it's your husband like
the devil yes on a bad day yes your
habit to see things the wrong way your
habit old habit who put it in your mind
yeah you did who put the sister yeah so
that's one kind of emptiness okay the
devil is also coming from your sins
okay the wrong way of looking at things
in your mind
whose fault I didn't do anything whose
fault yeah your phone okay bad deed
number 10 makes bad deed number 10 it's
the only one that makes itself over and
over okay got it
all right number 11 I taught you for
space meditation it's a big part of DCI
what level seven okay so there's a
famous meditation called nam kartoffel
which means what like space similar to
space okay and there's three ways to
misunderstand it so in DCI we teach
people to go through four ways of
meditating on empty space okay we go
through four ways and he's covering them
now
now the next few wrong meditations
are wrong meditations about the meaning
of space in Buddhism okay first one is
so easy it's gonna come later but let's
cover it okay
there's a abhidhamma school some very
low up during the time between the
Buddha's life and the gardener is
considered a bad days in Buddhism this
is when abhidharma became the worldview
okay this is Ann Inaba dharma was taught
by Buddha and it's a very beautiful
system but it has some important
mistakes in it which the Buddha put
there okay and one of them is that space
means the blue thing above you that's
empty space okay
blue what blue is a positive thing okay
it's it's a wrong idea
so those school called by básico
it became Buddhism for 600 years after
the Buddha's death abhidhamma and I
spent 12 years on abhidharma I I spent
12 years on it I know it and it's wrong
okay but it's useful to know you know
it's an important tool but it's wrong
okay but it became popular for five six
hundred years and it's spread to other
countries for five or six hundred years
anyway part of the abhidhamma view is
that space during meditation means blue
sky open your eyes look up that space
okay blue sky
janym sucked a supper manometer by
touching them such a country didn't
asanam kentucky burger Sammy Lanka
demand on too much innocent and nunca
Donna cope and the Dylan Anka Madiba
that's the opening lines of atomic OSHA
and that's where they say it's it's the
sky okay so one wrong idea about space
ready
that's for second one when you go past
the blue sky what's out there yeah black
space between the stars okay
so is it a meditation to go out at night
at Diamond Mountain and late we used to
lay down on the top of my house at
Diamond Mountain and stare at the sky
watch the stars it's very beautiful but
is that black thing emptiness is it real
space no okay it's not it's a color it's
a black color okay it's not emptiness
it's a positive thing emptiness is a
negative thing okay okay now third one
and I'm just telling you the next three
or four meditations because we do it in
DCI I put them all in one meditation so
you could feel the difference okay the
third one do you remember what's the
third one you are a city yeah nice I'll
kiss you but you're not so kissable
Stanley yeah empty space that one is
more subtle and and more close to
emptiness but it's not emptiness and
it's a difficult idea and you can only
see it with your mind you cannot see it
with your eyes okay
it's an idea okay ready
is this clock standing in space yeah it
has a place okay it has a place now
listen and try to understand that space
that place is not like your bathtub
okay it's not like your bathtub where
you take a bath okay it's not it's not
like that
when you get into your bathtub if the
water's up to the edge you know because
you did it when you're a kid and your
mom hates it you fill up the bathtub to
the very edge then you get in it goes
push and your mom says don't do that you
like mom and you said to take a bath you
know okay
so empty space doesn't mean when I put
the clock in the space some of the space
has to move
you know like water in the bathroom okay
those of you who know DC I you studied
in your nodding I love it it means you
are educated but generally it's
difficult to understand empty space
they had it many times they went to many
level sermons finally they understood it
okay now watch I'm gonna take the clock
out of the space
now I'm gonna occupy the space occupied
ocupado and then not occupying space is
occupied space is not occupied
okay the space doesn't have to move when
it's occupied because if it wasn't there
you couldn't put if something was
already in that space it would be
occupied
you see it's but it's not okay now when
I exit the space okay ready 1 2 3 is the
space still there good now I'll occupy
it is the space still there it has to be
there or the clock wouldn't fit you see
okay is the space unchanging yes okay
it's one of the few things in the world
which is unchanging okay
I didn't say eternal I said unchanging
okay it doesn't change occupied not
occupied the space is the same
that's good to think about to understand
emptiness it's not emptiness but it's
it's useful okay if you're really stupid
it's useful to look at the blue sky and
think about emptiness okay if you're
pretty stupid
then black outer space if you're less
stupid think about this one it will help
you okay but if you're intelligent
go to the fourth kind of space numb cut
double Akasha what is it
summer our precious summer real
emptiness real emptiness okay real
emptiness okay
what's done is there a Clarke which is
not coming from Geshe Michael no okay
that's all
is there any clock like that here no
let's go deeper could a clock which is
not coming from Geshe Michael exists no
impossible no such thing okay so what we
learn in DCI Saren emptiness is empty of
something not of something which could
exist it's empty of a thing which is
impossible okay impossible okay a
husband who's not coming from you a
husband who call you stupid who's not
coming from you
that kind of husband is impossible we
call gotcha right okay got it
when that husband when you see there's
no husband like that in your kitchen you
are doing namkha table you are doing a
special meditation called space like
space like it has a Buddhist name it's a
Buddhist name it's an emptiness
meditation is it space is it the blue
sky no is it the black outer space no is
it the place where I put the Clarke no
is it the husband who was never there
yeah
got it now we can study the next few
wrong meditations okay here we go
some people think about infinite space
and they mix it with the mind and they
meditate on that and they think that's a
space like meditation okay
what I can't figure out is why they
think that would hurt me okay
space is infinite sound familiar
come on come on give me the number give
me the number
nice I'll kiss you but you're too far
okay
meditation numbers fire okay nam kitab
oh that's numb Katara naan khatai yay
infinite space okay is it fun yes does
it expand your mind yes does it sharpen
your meditation skills yes will it keep
you from dying
no is it incompatible with the devil No
okay good and so I continue my
delightful dance here in those people's
minds okay got it
who's dancing where in the mind which is
thinking about blue sky or black space
or where I put the car okay got it
I love to dance in those mine they think
they got a taste they want to eat
they're hungry for emptiness they heard
about it they heard it was like space
they focus on empty place and they love
it and they think oh I'm better than
your emptiness it's such a pleasure to
to continue to live in the mind of a
person who's who thinks they're many
thing our emptiness and they're not it's
such a good joke you know I love it I
love to stay in this mind these people
they are meditate on emptiness they
don't understand anything
is soon it's especially sweet for the
devil okay
he dancing the smile forgotten it's like
super cool
okay it's when it come he likes it
oh you military antennas what's
emptiness nothing exist Oh dancing your
mind man I love your mind that's a great
meditation you keep doing that this is a
misunderstanding gardener and the
gardener said nothing starts nothing
stops okay it means without seed in your
mind okay without a seed nothing can
start without a seed nothing can stop
okay that's all then these people
misunderstood then and when a thought
comes they stare at it how did this
thought come from nothing okay
suddenly I'm thinking about something
pizza
I just think about pizza I wasn't
thinking about pizza five minutes ago
where'd that talk come from from nothing
oh that's emptiness okay they
misunderstand okay this one's easy we
don't have to talk about it why am i
rushing I don't know and then they say
when the thought slips away and there's
nothing left
that's the Dharmakaya that's the
Buddhist emptiness body okay
then there are a lot of weird ideas like
that okay
if a thought leaving your mind was the
reality body then you should try to have
as many random thoughts as possible okay
that's it now
this one's hard okay this one's hard
maybe you need a break
you know what you want I think man you
need a break take a 10-minute break come
back no no
what we're gonna do next the devil in
the mind is the lower-middle way school
so you need peepee before done this is
not a stupid devil this was
sophisticated
okay lower middle way okay go 10 minutes
or I'll ring the bell
[Music]
so those of you who came to SC I am last
term I think second term we talked about
the proofs for emptiness and there's one
called chick to dough
what's that mean yeah things are neither
one nor many okay this is a proof of
emptiness there's another proof called
dorje sec malware stun this sliver of
diamond and there are there's a group of
proofs of emptiness that I taught you in
a CI - they say of course - okay what I
didn't tell you at the time was that
those are mostly used by the
lower-middle way okay most of those are
they are mostly used by the lower-middle
way circle the dependent origination
argument is is shared by both okay
typically but so there's a proof of
emptiness which is used by the lower
middle school a lot which means people
like Kamala Sheila Shanta rock sheet of
vivica okay
and they'll they they like those proofs
okay and I'm gonna tell you what they
believe and then it's enough for tonight
and we'll continue next class okay
because here the first punch in llama
begins to talk about proofs for
emptiness or meditations on emptiness
which are Buddhists and they are
lower-middle way and they they make the
devil uncomfortable but they don't kick
him out
okay so we're about to learn some
meditations that are they make the devil
uncomfortable but they don't force him
out of your mind okay
so they are nice to learn they are
partly correct but they're not
ultimately crying okay and they will not
force the devil to leave your mind
okay so we've been describing how the
seeds open in your mind just before you
see emptiness directly you see seeds
open in your mind okay you can call that
dependent origination okay when you can
see seeds actually open and create
something in front of you you've seen
depend origination for the first time
okay because your mind is doing it 65
times per second all the time
okay what's the classic example for that
in a DCI level seven nice I'll kiss you
but you have a beard you used to have a
beard
yeah it's a you okay this is a story you
know the student is standing in the
kitchen they are making tea for their
nama and they are waiting for the water
to boil and they have all the conditions
for making enough karma to see emptiness
directly okay which include what serving
serving poor people serving needy people
serving elderly okay that's one
secondly meditate every day minimum one
hour if you do a nice lion stance you're
covered number three
by the way in DC is a half hour if I say
one hour they will go home okay third
one you served the Dharma somehow served
the Dharma okay help organize her income
door you know did something help the
Dharma okay what else
yoga helps study study study study study
study okay somebody recently came to me
they said geshe-la
I'm leaving I said why did they say you
teach too much
that's like there's a joke in Buddhism
they say that's like saying I'm really
hungry but I don't feel like eating
so anyway by the way in their present
paramita tradition the most intelligent
students want more proofs of emptiness
they want more information they're
hungry they want more okay
it's a classic way to divide a good
student from a lazy student or a good
student from a student who's not ready
yet okay the good students want they say
a thousand proofs of emptiness that's
this expression that Lord Buddha used
you know the good student wants to hear
emptiness a thousand different ways and
the other students like too much
information you know okay I like the
first kind of student because I like to
anyway so anyway when you're looking at
the pot on the stove there are parts
there okay there are parts out there the
typically in that case three parts three
main parts one black straight thing
which is what handle then there's a
silver circle which is the top and sorry
there's silver circle and black okay
three parts then the seed opens in the
mind and you can see the image go out
okay standing there you don't have to be
in meditation is it emptiness no it's
dependent origination here comes the car
here comes the pot it's this big it's
been staying here okay it comes out of a
Silverson it goes out and then it lands
on the pieces and it makes them into a
pot okay the same pieces
if you have the seeds of an ant make a
silver mountain okay the ants picture is
off Mount Everest silver difficult to
climb okay same parts different picture
okay
now the difference between the higher
middle school and the lower middle way
school mainly is who put the parts there
yeah okay I did they all they came from
me a moment before the other picture
okay first a seed open for silver color
then the seed opened for round then the
seed open for black straight then the
seed open for pot okay so who made the
raw data yeah
now the lower middle way school says no
they say the silver was there already
and your mind is interpreting the silver
okay it's not creating this silver your
mind is taking the information okay like
Neil Young song or Scotts song tonight
okay then some people explain emptiness
what Oh geshe-la
some people like the song and some
people don't like the song although
we're not gonna tell Scott and that's
the emptiness of the song okay but but
it's it's not that emptiness is how you
interpret the some emptiness is who made
the song okay we are not interpreting
the same song we are creating this song
okay it's different right when you say
I'm interpreting his song I like it and
then some people say I don't like it
both people are assuming there's a song
okay some people say there's a song and
I don't like it and some people say
there's a song and I do like it both of
them think the song is coming from Scott
understand okay
higher middle way Scott also covered
from me okay song also coming from me
okay got it lower middle way you can
call them interpreters the interpret was
there is this silver thing a mountain or
is it a teapot you see but both of those
people believe there's something there
but there's none okay before your mind
made the silver before your mind made
Scott okay there was nothing okay it's
not Scott came in and sang a song and
some people like it and some people
don't like it that's not emptiness okay
emptiness is you made Scott first and
then two minutes later you decided to
sell the this song sound good or bad
okay got it
lower middle way says you didn't create
Scott you didn't create this silver
color
okay got it okay now so every time they
use the reasons for emptiness that were
given by the Buddha they misunderstand
them okay even they teach the proof of
one and many to prevent eNOS they prove
emptiness with the proof of one and many
but they prove it the wrong way they
don't understand they use the proof they
come to some emptiness and it's not a
genius
okay now is that gonna hurt the devil
not really okay it is like well they're
getting close Oh
where'd the silver come from oh it was
there uh-huh okay you can stay come on
in
with me well I was afraid you were gonna
say this silver wasn't there you know
okay okay got it
okay so the whole next few parts which
we will do next weekend we'll do some
more okay they're gonna be more subtle
this this text is unbelievable it's
funny it's very poetic and it's very
deep because he even criticized
middle-way you see he even said you are
devil also you know probably they were
killing my I think these are Kamala
Sheila this is big Lamas you know and he
said no you don't quite understand
you're also helping the devil when I
teach you karma Sheila I'm teaching you
the gardener combination ah okay so
don't worry about it okay he he also
taught some lower middle way but he did
I believe he didn't believe it okay he
taught it for certain people because
they feel uncomfortable if Scott's not
there I got it okay all right
luckily it's time to stop and I'll see
you in them okay so we stopped at
ineffective meditation number 13 I don't
know you guys compare your notes 13 we
didn't cover yet 13 is lower middle way
and they are going to misuse the
meditation on one or many
okay got it you try to figure out what
the first 12 I'll say them again next
time okay then you guys don't have to
fight all right